So as you can see what the picture on the screen. Each finger is dedicated to a certain part of the keyboard for example if you want to type the r keyword you want to start with your index finger.
If you want to type p you are going to do it with your right hand. Pinky finger. Things like that so that is the basic layout of touch typing and one thing to note.
That is really important is to make sure that you type with accuracy and not speed speed will come after but first you want to make sure that what you're doing is correct considering that is a very strict the.
@@@
So i'm going to keep the. Layout of the picture on the screen just in case for anyone wanting to use it as a reference but right now let's get into the instructions on how to actually properly touch type and although there's not many instructions to really start off with most of the instructions that are strict make touch typing strict is based off of the the fingers which fingers to use for which key but to start off with the starting position.
Make sure that your index fingers or on the f and j if you look down at your keyboard you're most likely going to find that there's small little ridges.
Under these keys and that's where your index fingers are supposed to go. The remained nder of your other fingers your three fingers and the thumb I'll.
Show you afterwards. Go on the keys. To the left or to the right so f and j or your index. Your middle fingers are going to go on the next ones. Your ring fingers are going to go on the next ones and then your pinky fingers are going to go on the next ones so your hand for your left should go a s d f.
And your right hand should go j k l and then colon. Everytime you type for example let's type test. You go. T with their index oh and make sure you immediately go back to home.
So you type t. Then you go back to home. Then with your middle finger you'd go to eat. Then you'd go back to home. Then with your ring finger you would go to s then he'd go back to home which anyways that's already home and then you'd go with your index finger back city and then back to home and that's pretty much it those are really the only three rules that you have to keep in mind when touch typing make sure that your forefingers each hand.
@@@
So two really good websites that I've found to practice touch typing. They're going to be linked in the course but it is typing study and key br dot com.
Typing study is like this. You they show you the reason why i like this one more is because whenever you want to press a key it shows you which finger you even want to use to press so for example a a.
And your thumbs are space. And it's ss and dd. And f f. Right so it shows you which fingers that you need to use and eventually it builds you up into.
Stuff like this and. Actual words. Salad eventually these are words but. It goes into numbers and then it goes into. If you go down into here and. Yeah so it goes into larger words and it shows you how to properly do it and with proper keys the second typing practice that i encourage you to do is.
Key b r and you you don't have to i no there's a lot of ads and it doesn't go through an ad block but it is pretty helpful because it shows you right here which keys you need to press and it gives you the words so are.
And then you see that the pinkie is a and then you see that the. Index is also. Index or tea is also index and and then he is apart of the middle finger those are probably two of the best touch typing practices that you should use in order to practice touch typing.
Make sure that you practice the words for the fundamentals i can't stress this enough. You have to make sure that your typing accuracy over speed because.
If you're just going straight for speed. You're going to completely disregard the rules completely disregard the proper finger placements and you're not even touch typing at all right.
@@@
Whenever i teach the two methods i always get the question is touch typing harder and i always say it depends. Personally for me it is a very strict rule set for your fingers and for how you can actually type and this strict ruleset makes you makes it so you don't have a a leeway.
For when you make an error for example if you type. One one key with a finger you're not supposed to use and this strict rule set is why i think it's a little bit more difficult than unconventional typing because of this lack of leeway for error but at the end of the day.
What's hard and what's not is again dependent on the person if you think that something that has strict rule sets is easier then. By all means it's easier but from the experience that I've had teaching students.
@@@
Regardless of which method you use of unconventional what you're about to learn or touch typing which you have already learned. Any form of typing will help touch typing specifically helps you build the proper fundamentals that is.
The foundation of every single method having your hands where they're supposed to be place on the keyboard and how to properly type without putting strain on your wrists having those fundamentals is so much better than having nothing at all when typing because having those fundamentals knowing where to put your keys knowing what to do with this and that.
Allows you to type more efficiently with less strain on your wrists. Then you would have if you didn't have those fundamentals so i think that touch typing is an amazing introductory method into how to type because of those reasons.
@@@
So there's no real direct layout with unconventional typing but just know that again type with accuracy and not speed the speed will come naturally and similar to touch typing.
So one conventional typing is a little bit more interesting because it allows you to. Feel more comfortable while you're typing and that's exactly why i like it.
So I'll show you my way of unconventional typing which is most likely going to be the way that you do it kind of but it's not going to be necessarily the same so if it's not then don't worry but it's going to have the same general rules of what you can be what you most likely will adapt to the unconventional way of typing has left hand right hand dominant and I'll show exactly what that means so for example if i wanted to type i love you.
Right i would type i love. I love. And then. I type y with the index finger which is normal. O with the. Ring or the middle finger which a normal but then i would type.
You with also the index finger and if you noted from touch typing that should be the right hand index finger and not the left hand. And that's what i mean the unconventional way of typing we'll make it so one hand will most likely be more dominant on the keyboard than the other and that's completely fine eventually you just kind of realize which hand it is and there's no reason to change it whatsoever so for this typing method essentially you kind of just type whichever or wherever your fingers or closest to.
So. You're typing the rough general starting spot is the fundamental touch typing area right here. But then sometimes you can. Type e. With your. Index finger.
This may seem closer but sometimes it's not and that's the thing. It's an art form some tea times you may type however you want it's just it depends it really just depends on the muscle memory that you build but most of the time.
You're going to be typing with whatever fingers are closer to you so for example if your hand is all the way over here. Right if you're typing the apostrophe.
Sometimes you will type i with your left hand or your b or your n and that's because it's just simply closer and that's the muscle memory you're going to develop.
And thus the other thing as well the other the other piece of muscle memory you're going to be developing. Is leaving your fingers where you last type them so contrary to two touch typing.
Whenever you type for example t. You're going to go back to home but in unconventional typing you're going to be typing in a way that if you type t. You're going to leave it at t.
And that's how that whole thing kind of meshes together whenever. You type it's going to stay there and and. When you type. The closest finger will be dependent on where it was last left off when you finished typing a word however you're going to take a break you're obviously going to go back in the middle if you type test.
You're going to go back in the middle. You don't want to stay in that position like that because then that's just completely uncomfortable. And you. Is just not efficient so you most likely go back.
@@@
The way to practice unconventional typing is by finding a website a good website that allows you to have a lot of variability and the website that i recommend is monkey type as you can see you can cycle through a bunch of different options.
And as such allows you to experiment and build more muscle memory and as a practice i want to give you a kind of routine. On monkey type so unconventional typing requires a lot on muscle memory and to build that muscle memory there's a lot of practice that goes into it and i want to give you a balanced routine you can do.
In order to build that muscle memory without overdoing it so the three exercises that i want you to do and they're going to be on the screen are as follows five times fifteen seconds five times words twenty five and three times short quote and i want you to do this once a day but make sure that you're also focusing on accuracy over speed and you're not overdoing it you're not spamming your keyboard and making sure or that you prioritize your rest health over everything else so I'll show you what each exercise looks like and this is the time fifteen so essentially you have fifteen seconds to just type out.
The words that are given. And remember focus on accuracy over speed don't spam don't make a costly mistake makes cause then those mistakes will just become habits second one is five times worse twenty five and essentially there is no time limit so you can take your time don't rush.
Is just typing out. The words in the sentence until it reaches twenty five words and lastly. Three times short quotes this is the one that i think is most important because it incorporates punctuation so you see there's a comma here.
You see that. There's a. You saw a semi-colon. More commas. You see another semi-colon so it kind of help makes you adapt to which to use lastly before you do all of this make sure you're taking regular breaks and that you're focusing i can't stress this enough accuracy over speed you don't want to incorporate bad habits into your typing because then that may compromise your health and that may compromise your speed in the future.
@@@
Another question similarly to touch typing is often ask about unconventional typing which is does it even help you know you have no rules said you have no guidelines you have no idea of what errors are.
How do you know the fundamentals and i'd argue that to an extent they're right you don't have any guidelines of errors and you don't know what you're doing wrong however the fundamentals are still there regardless of your touch typing regardless of your unconventionally typing.
Regardless of what. Method you're using to type. You're going to have to use the fundamentals and unconventionally typing the reason why i think it helps is because because it doesn't have a strict rule set but you're still using the fundamentals it allows you to experiment outside see if anything is quicker for you see if anything is more comfortable more flexible for you and that's why i kind of like unconventional little bit better because it fits with the person rather than fitting with the strict rule set that they may not really like so if you're more accustomed the two following the rules and you know having those guidelines then by all means touch type but if you want to experiment a little bit.
@@@
So now there's going to be some techniques to actually learn how to type faster and the first technique is to how to stop looking at the keyboard the way to stop looking at the keyboard depends on muscle memory it's just practice practice practice to know which keys are aware on your keyboard but.
The thing that has helped me a lot and has helped my other students a lot when it comes to typing is to cover the keyboard this can be done in various ways you can put a cloth over it you can.
If you have a second compartment to your desk you can put it there. And then just type without it and then once you do events really you'll get accustomed to the keyboard and you you'll you'll stop looking at it once you cover it you're going to have to force yourself to know where the keys are so my best suggestion to stop looking for the keyboard.
@@@
The best way to describe it is through an analogy of riding a bike when you first started riding a bike you had no idea how to pedal what you did but it wasn't flowing correctly you weren't switching through the gears right.
You may have fallen once or twice and that is just how you learn as how you started you had no rhythm but once you kept at it and once you practice a little bit more that is when you developed the proper rhythm in order to ride a bike and keep keyboard typing is the exact same eventually after a bunch of practice.
You're just going to wake up one day with rhythm and and i'm seriously not joking right now it may seem like i'm just saying that but one day you're going to just see that oh well might my typing is just flowing super well and thus just because you practice but you have to make sure you practice because reality is sometimes you type faster and sometimes you don't but all that matters is that you have that practice with the rhythm and the best way to practice that i found is through a game called type racer.
As you see on the screen type racer is just this. And you're given a prompt to type and u-verse other people. And this is how it looks like right so you're going a bunch of other people.
And. You're going to have to type out the prompt that you're given. Like salt. And anyways my recommendation is to once in a while type a little bit faster than you're accustomed to especially on typewriter it's a very good website to do so.
Because you're competing with others. And once you get accustomed to this speed you may not get accustomed to it at all all. Right you could be just jumping on your word all the time but when you go back to practice and you slow it down a little bit you'll realize that.
Because you tried typing so fast. Your body is slowly getting accustomed to typing that slow and you're you're quite literally develop a rhythm because of that.
@@@
One of the other important ways of typing faster is auto correct and this is just an example of text predictions when doing autofill so this is an exit poll and you see that it's the rest of it is highlighted in grey and all you just do is press tab and it just off auto fills perfectly for you autofill will predict what you're going to say and.
Most of the time it's correct so whenever you see grey words popping up while you're typing just press tab it'll autofill for you and that i think is the most under used feature that a lot of people.
@@@
At the end of the day it all comes down to this. Practice. You have to practice practice practice regardless of what method you're using and what technique you want to quickly speed up the typing there's no shortcut to learning how to type quicker and more efficiently than to just simply practice and because practicing is literally the most important thing for typing.
So as previously mentioned the best tools to practice are the ones that I've mentioned previously so caviar you have typing study monkey type you have type racer all of which are going to be.
Available to you as a link through the course but those are the best tools to practice because it emphasizes on a lot of different aspects when it comes to typing.
You have speed you have accuracy you have the different components of the keyboard you have semicolons you have the q you have the p of the z all of. Different angles of the keyboard that you have to practice through these games and to be quite honest i have to contribute my fast typing speed to these games because they've all helped me to pinpoint on my weak parts and allow me to work on them and strengthening my entire keyboard style up so make sure that you play these games regularly because these games are literally the exact key.
@@@
And lastly i think the most important thing to do when practicing his track your progress in the course i'm going to have. A tracking progress master sheet and i hope to utilize it because it will show you where you came from and will show you how far you progress showing how far you progress is a great indicator into what you're doing right what you're doing wrong and ensuring that you stay on the track if you're doing it right and changing the track if you're doing it wrong so i always suggest my students to track your progress because then you'll be able to know what you're doing right what you're doing wrong and what you should choose change when you look in the section you'll find that there's a downloadable progress tracker sheet and essentially what i previously just said in terms of monitoring and tracking your progress and tracking your strengths your weaknesses and your changes.
This sheet i specifically made to ensure you do all of that so i'm going to walk through this progress to tracker she and show you how it works and why you should use it to the first page is essentially just the graph sheet so you're going to start off by putting the words per minute that you're starting off before you start this program and it's just going to show off some a basic instruction saying that you shouldn't add the values in here.
On your own but essentially this is just going to be the visual graph representation of how your progress is throughout the weeks. The second page is actually going to be where you put all your information so you see that each day is going to have a certain amount of words per minute and essentially if you read the instructions these words from senate are just going to be the highest words per minute that you did for that day so you see that every day for ten to fifteen minutes practice typing through the games learned in the course and record your results of your highest words per minute.
So whatever game you do if you do monkey type if you do keep jar if you do typewriter. Record the hype as words per minute that you did for that day and essentially after the seven days passes you're going to have an average for that week so for example if i type in twenty nine and i'm tempted then five and then i do forty one day forty one i go back down to twenty nine.
Point the five hundred and fifty. This is going to populate as the average of all these numbers and and you'll see also that's how the graph works as well the third sheet is going to be the same thing with weeks one to thirteen and it's just going to be the comments that you're going to leave for each week if you want to update daily then go ahead if you want to update a weekly that's what i'd suggest but everyone is different so you see that here's an example of what the comment is going to look like and you see that in the instructions they're out it's outlined as to what you should write out so your strengths your weaknesses and the changes for the next week so for example if you were touch typing one of the strengths could be my left hand was typing in the proper position so your left hand was going back to home after each word.
Your left fingers were properly typing or hitting the keys it was supposed to and what not. A weakness was i was unable to use my ring finger properly so if you're using your left hand or your right hand could be.
Bow both. Ah your ring finger might not be as. Present. When typing because that's not how people are accustomed to typing so it could just be that. Your ring finger was not being properly utilized and a simple change most likely will come from your weakness and it's just to make sure that your ring finger for the next week on your hand is used to type the proper letters that it needs to type such as a simple three point comment of your strengths weaknesses and changes will definitely help in the long run as if you are in week two week three week four whatnot.
You look back in the previous week's comments see what your strength is what your strengths were. You'll focus less on those and then see what your weaknesses were and you'll say to yourself okay i need to prioritize this for this week and lastly the last page is simply just a page that i used for calculations in order to populate the graph so just do not you can see do not or do not touch this page but other than that that is pretty much the rundown of the progress tracker and the reason why you should use it is because not only will.
If you go to week eleven week twelve you'll see how far you've come but again for the comments especially you'll see what to work on for the from the weaknesses and the changes from the previous weeks.
@@@
The reason you should learn shortcuts is. As mentioned previously in the first section there are multiple benefits to typing properly and efficiently and one of them was productivity learning the shortcuts allows you to flow more fluently through your work make it easier more seamless while you're doing your work and allows you to speed up the time that you're.
So the first two shortcuts are actually going to be the most important ones that i found and control a is essentially just being able to highlight everything on the page.
Simply that. So if you have a bunch of text here taste as test as whatever. Control a allows you to highlight all of that and allow you to do whatever you want with it you can press delete you can delete it all and the next keyboard shortcut actually relates with control a but control a essentially just allows you to highlight everything on the page.
@@@
Other shortcut that is often used with control as control c and control siege stands for control copying what it does is suppress it. You're not going to see what happens but.
It gets copied to your clipboard and within allows you to do. Is paste it which is the exact same shortcut i'm going to be talking about next but just know that control c k copies a text so for example if you just want a copy this.
Boom just like that and you want to paste. Just like that right but if you want to use the shortcut that we used before control a. And then control c for copy and then you just control paste again ashes can control.
@@@
So control v is very very often used with control c and what it is is just control paste. So as you saw in the previous demonstration you do control a.
Control a control c for copy. And you can go here and do that but. You can do control a. Control c and then when you press control v. It automatically copies for you we can do this how many times as you want.
@@@
Control z is the shortcut the keyboard shortcut for allowing you to and do. So as you saw i typed a bunch of other stuff here and unlike one oh i don't want this to be here so you just press control z.
And one by one. It will. Undo. So for example whenever you're typing out a sentence this is an example of and you just want to control or you want to undo the entire sentence.
@@@
So control f actually stands for control find and this works for every document it works for every web page and essentially it just allows to find certain text within wherever you're searching so for example if i want to find the word hello i just press control f.
A prompt is going to pop up and you just type in. Hello and it will highlight the word and it will also provide all of the instances so for example if there's multiple of them.
When i type in hello. Ill type in all of the instances and one highlight all of the times it does say hello. Or in the sidebar so just know that control f.
@@@
So essentially what control and is as it's not used for any documents but it is used for web pages for browsers i opened up Microsoft edge and when you could press control and.
It will create a new tab. As many times as you want and it will just create the new tab as you see. And. That's that's pretty much it it can troll and just allows you to create a new tab.
@@@
And the last shortcut of the course is control. H in what this does is it allows you it opens up a prompt for find and replace so if you press control age.
It will show up this screen that allows you to find. A text and replace it with something else for example if i have hello in the find what it's going to search the text the entire text for hello.
And i want to replace it with. Adam. It will replace every instance of hello with every answer to every instance of Adam so replace all. And boom just like that.
Every single instance of hello is replaced with Adam and now. If we use the other shortcuts we use control z and then we do control h. You'll see that.
The first instance if you just press replace it will only go with the first instance. And then oh go onto the second instance. And then that's that so replaces one by one and replace all his all at once.
@@@
I just want to say quickly before we end the course. If you have any questions if you have any inquiries comments feedbacks anything. I'm always here if you want to comment down below or comment in the comment section.
Thank you for making it to the end of the course and i hope you learned something new if you have i'd appreciate if you rate the course five stores or if you have any feedback i also appreciate that too as i'd want to keep the course regularly updated.